In this video, we will be going over two
momentum
problems. And before that, we will learn
about
elastic versus inelastic momentum
collisions.
So, first of all, what are elastic
collisions?
Elastic collisions are collisions that do
not
have energy lost. So, that means that
there
is a conservation of momentum and a
conservation
of energy. However, on the other hand,
inelastic
collisions have a loss of energy.
Even though momentum is conserved, there
will
be a loss of energy. I'll show you what I
mean
in these questions. So, first of all, our
first
question is a 2kg cart moving at 4m per
second
collides elastically with a 1kg cart
initially
at rest on a frictionless track.
And you want to calculate the final
velocities
of both carts. So, if we think about this,
there
will be a cart over here weighing 2kg and
it
is going at 4m per second.
And there is a cart with 1kg and it is at
rest, so it has a speed of 0m per second.
And we want to calculate the final
velocities
of both carts. Now, let's first use the
conservation
of momentum we got here.
The total momentum of the system is always
the
same. So, P before equals the sum of the
momentums after. So, what are the
momentums
before? Well, there is the momentum of
this
cart, let's call this cart A, and the
momentum
of this cart, call this cart B.
Now, the momentum of cart A is mass times
velocity,
so mass A times vA.
And that is mass B times vB.
But you notice that cart B is at rest,
which
means vB is 0. So, this whole expression
will
be equal to 0. So, the total momentum of
the
system is only that of cart A.
Now, for cart, the total momentum after,
what
we have is the mass of A, which is
constant,
the final velocity of cart A, so vA final.
The mass of B, and the final velocity of
this
cart, so vB final.
And also don't forget that these are
unknowns.
So, we just need to first plug in our
numbers.
The mass here is 2, velocity is 4, the
mass
here is 2 vAF plus 1, or just
vBF. So, we get 8 equals 2 vAF plus vBF.
And now, we are left with this equation,
with
two unknowns. How do we solve this
problem?
Well, the next thing we have to consider
is
since it's an elastic collision, energy is
conserved.
Now, if energy is conserved, that means
that
the total Ke before, Ke before, is
equal to the total kinetic energy after.
So, the total kinetic energy before is 1
over
2 ma vA squared.
And there's no kinetic energy in B because
it's
not moving, the speed is 0. The total
kinetic
energy after is 1 over 2 ma vAF, the final
velocity
squared, plus 1 over 2 mB vBF squared.
Now, all of these 1 over 2's cancel out
when
you factor them, and now we can start
putting
in numbers. So, ma is 2, I believe, 2
kilograms,
and velocity is 4, so 4 squared times 2
would
be 32. 2 vAF squared
plus vBF squared, since mB is 1.
And now, what we can do is we can just
solve
our numbers.
We have vAF and we have vBF, which means
that
we have 2 equations with 2 unknowns.
Now, this is just simple math, so you can
see
how physics kind of relates to math, in a
sense.
So, I'm just going to really quickly do
this.
I see that vBF can be substituted in.
vBF equals 8 minus 2 vAF.
So, I'm going to substitute that into this
equation.
So, what I'll get is 32 equals 2 vAF
squared plus 8 minus 2 vAF squared.
And now, we can just solve that. So, 32
equals...
Let's call vAF x, so it's easier.
I don't have to write vAF every single
time.
So, 32 equals 2x squared plus 64 minus 32x
plus 4x squared.
And now, we just continue solving this.
32 equals 6x squared plus 64 minus 32x.
So, 0 equals 3x squared.
I'm moving this to the side and dividing
by
2. Plus 16x plus 16.
And when we solve for x using the
quadratic
formula or factoring, I think you can only
use
the quadratic formula here. So, 16 plus
root
16 squared minus 4, 3, 16 over
2 times 3. You would get x is equal to 4.
And you would also get x is equal to 1.33
metres per second. Now, how do you know
which
one is the right answer?
Well, you know that the initial speed of
this
cart is 4 metres per second. So, when it's
transferring
energy, what we solved is the possible
speeds
of the carts. And you know this is the
initial,
so we want the final. So, x must be 1.33.
So, the final speed of cart A must be 1.33
metres
per second. And this would be your answer
for
this cart. Now, one final step is to
calculate
the speed of the other cart, just plugging
this
into this formula. So, we get vbf equals 8
minus
2vaf, which is 1.33.
And you would get 5.33 metres
per second. And that would be your final
answer
for cart 2. And so, you can see how we can
relate
momentum with conservation of energy.
And this is basically how you do it for
elastic
collisions. Now, however, what if the
collisions
are inelastic? Well, if it's inelastic,
then
momentum is conserved, but energy is lost.
And I find inelastic collisions way, way
easier,
it's way, way faster as well, because
there's
also no big math calculations like we had
to
do over here. Let's see this question.
A 0.5 kilogram ball moving at 6 metres per
second
collides with a 1.5 kilogram stationary
ball,
or a ball at rest, 1.5 kg and 0.5.
And it's moving at 6 metres per second.
After the collisions, the two balls stick
together.
When they stick together, you know the
collision
is inelastic. And the
question didn't state what you want to
solve,
but let's say you want to solve the final
speed
of both balls, both balls, and be
the loss of kinetic energy, loss of Ke.
Now, the final speed of each ball is the
same
because they stick together, and we can
use
the conservation of momentum to do this.
And this time we don't have two different
variables
because the final speed is the same. So
once
they collide, you can think of them as one
system,
a combined mass moving at a certain amount
of
speed, and that's what we want to find. So
the
combined mass would be 0.5 plus 1.5, which
is
2 kg. So using the conservation of
momentum,
we know that P, let's call this ball A and
ball
B, the momentum of A plus the momentum of
B
is equal to the momentum of A plus B,
because
after they collide, they stick together,
and
you can treat it as one system. The
momentum
of A is equal to 0.5 times 6.
The momentum of B is equal to 1.5 times 0,
which
is 0. And the momentum of both the
things after they stick together is their
total
mass, which we calculated over here, 0.5
plus
1.5, times their final speed.
So 0.5 times 6 is 3, and 0.5 plus 1.5 is 2
times
vf. So that's pretty straightforward.
We get the final velocity of both balls is
1.5
m per second. That would be your final
answer
for A. Now, let's move on to question B.
Question B asks us for the loss of Ke.
Well, the loss of kinetic energy could be
written
as the initial kinetic energy value minus
the
final kinetic energy value, because that
would
be the loss. And the initial kinetic
energy
is the total kinetic energy of both balls.
Ball B is stationary, so it doesn't have
any
kinetic energy. So ball A is basic.
The kinetic energy in ball A is the total
kinetic
energy initially. So it would be 1 over 2
ma
va squared minus, and now after, when both
systems
are combined and there is only one big
system,
it is minus 1 over 2 times the combined
mass
times the combined speed squared.
I would factor out 1 over 2 over here.
Mass of A is 0.5.
The velocity is 6, so 6 squared minus mass
of
AB is 2. The velocity of AB is what we
calculated
over here, so 1.5 squared.
And now it's just a matter of calculating.
I will just type this directly in my
calculator,
because we have shown basically all the
logic
steps. Times 1.5 squared.
And you'll get 6.75 joules of energy lost.
And that will be your final answer for
part
B. And that's it on how to solve elastic
collisions.
And elastic collisions. So just remember,
elastic
collisions energy is conserved, and you
will
likely end up with two different formulas
that
you will have to solve for this. However,
in
elastic equations, you will likely only
have
to solve one formula, because the systems
combine
into one big system, so you're just
solving
for whatever you want for that one big
system.
Thank you, and I hope you learned how to
solve
these types of problems.